I hear from lots of
people every day
who are concerned about how
their diet is affecting their health.
They need answers
based on facts.
In other words,
in the peer-reviewed
medical literature,
and that is what
I’m here for.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we discover that
anatomy may not be destiny.
It turns out that in some countries 85%
of menopausal women suffer hot flashes.
But in other countries that
number's only 15%.
Here’s our first story.
SWAN, which stands for Study
of Women’s Health Across the Nation,
is by far the largest evaluation
of menopausal symptoms in history,
studying 16,000 American women
between the ages of 40 and 55.
They found that women over
a body mass index of 27 or higher
were significantly more likely to suffer
from hot flashes or night sweats,
stiffness or soreness,
and urinary leakage.
A BMI over 25 is considered overweight;
30 is obese;
and the average U.S. BMI is 29.8.
Since fatty tissue is a source for estrogen
one might expect the reverse,
but the link between excess body fat
and worse menopausal symptoms
indeed seems causal since women
randomized to a weight loss intervention
experience significant improvement
in hot flashes,
an effect that may extend
to bariatric surgery.
In the SWAN study,
smoking and inactivity
were also associated
with more frequent symptoms.
It’s always a good idea
to quit smoking and exercise,
but there are no interventional trials
on smoking cessation
and menopausal symptoms
to prove cause-and-effect,
and randomized controlled trials of exercise
failed to show any symptom relief.
Of course you could just
take hormone therapy,
but at the cost of significantly higher risk
of suffering a heart attack,
stroke, blood clot, breast cancer,
or gallbladder disease.
What can we do naturally to avoid
the extra clots and cancer?
Hot flashes, also referred to
as hot flushes,
are the most common menopausal symptom
for which women seek treatment.
They afflict up to 80 to 85 percent
of European and American women,
lasting, along with night sweats,
for an average of more than seven years.
But these symptoms are not universal.
Though in North America
they may be considered inevitable,
if you noticed in Japan, for example,
only 15 percent may be affected.
In fact, there isn’t even a term
for hot flash in the Japanese language.
The absence of even a word for it
in Japan is all the more remarkable
because Japanese is said to be
“infinitely more sensitive” than English
in describing bodily states,
with all sorts of extremely subtle
distinctions for somatic sensations.
For example, there are all sorts of specific
terms describing different sensations.
In Japanese there are 20
or more words just to describe
the state of one's stomach
and intestines alone.
But hot flashes appear
to be so unusual there,
researchers had to come up with ways
to describe it in Japanese surveys.
Investigators suspected
it might be the soy.
Dietary surveys have estimated
that soy isoflavone intake,
the phytoestrogens in soy,
is at least ten times higher
than in Europe or North America.
And one comparison
of urine metabolites revealed
Japanese women have a hundred times
more phytoestrogens
flowing through their body
at any one time.
To see if this might be playing a role,
researchers followed
a thousand Japanese women over time,
starting before they reached menopause,
to see if soy consumption was linked
to whether or not
they developed hot flashes.
Women eating around four ounces
of tofu a day only had half the risk
compared to women only eating
an ounce or two a day.
The researchers concluded, “Our findings
suggest that consumption of soy products
is a practical strategy
for preventing hot flashes.”
But only if interventional trials prove
they actually work,
which I’ll cover next.
Is the consumption of soy
the reason why there isn’t even a word
for hot flash in Japanese?
Approximately 80% of perimenopausal
and postmenopausal women surveyed
choose to try natural means
to deal with symptoms,
and the single most common approach
was soy. But does it work?
Outside of an Asian context,
soy milk may be
a greater source of isoflavones
than soy foods,
and that seems ready-made
for a randomized trial
against dairy milk
or another plant milk control.
Soy milk consumption has been associated
with fewer hot flashes and night sweats
and skim milk
with worse menopausal symptoms,
but when actually put to the test
against each other
there does not appear
to be any difference.
There have been studies showing
that randomizing women to soy milk
can reduce hot flashes
and vaginal symptoms
as much as 70%
compared to the control group,
but without a placebo control,
we’re not sure how much of that
is the placebo effect.
To truly blind study subjects,
soy isoflavones were extracted out
and stuffed into capsules
to be pitted against identical looking
“sugar pill” placebo capsules.
More than a dozen such clinical studies
have been performed—
randomized double-blind,
placebo-controlled trials
—and indeed, the equivalent of about
two servings of soy foods a day worth
reduced hot flash frequency
by about 20% more than placebo
and hot flash severity by around
25% more than placebo,
compared to more like
a 30 to 40% net reduction
from estrogen hormone therapy.
Soy isoflavones have also been shown
to improve other menopausal concerns
including vaginal dryness, bone loss,
memory and cognitive functions
more generally,
as well as depression.
There have been a few trials
in which soy was pitted head-to-head
against hormone therapy.
One found their efficacy comparable,
in terms of reducing hot flashes,
muscle and joint pain,
and vaginal dryness.
In the other, hormones worked
twice as well,
a 54% reduction in hot flash scores
taking the standard
estrogen/progesterone combination
compared to 24% over placebo
in the soy isoflavone group.
Not only did the hormones work better,
but they can work quicker.
Three months are required
for soy isoflavones to achieve
half their maximal effect,
whereas the same is achieved
after just three weeks with estrogen.
Of course, soy has the benefit
of no increased risk
of cancer and clots.
In fact, if anything,
a reduction in breast cancer risk
throughout the lifespan, and lower
risk of cardiovascular disease.
The bottom line, wrote one
consensus panel of experts,
is that soy can be considered
a first-line treatment
for menopausal hot flash
and night sweat symptoms.
One convenient whole food source
of soy is soy nuts,
which are dry roasted soybeans.
Harvard Medical School’s Center
of Excellence in Women’s Health
funded a randomized crossover study
of a half cup of unsalted soy nuts a day
(divided into three or four portions
and spaced throughout the day)
and achieved a 50% reduction
in hot flashes within two weeks.
What’s inconvenient about soy nuts
is the formation of advanced glycation
end products in the roasting process,
though about four times less than
that of roasted real nuts,
or other roasted legumes,
and ten times less than a serving
of something like roasted chicken,
but something like edamame
or canned soybeans would be better.
Some menopausal women
use isoflavone supplements,
but most just add soy foods
to their diet.
I think that’s the way to go.
Supplement mislabeling
and contamination issues aside,
though isolated isoflavones have been
shown to improve artery function
and decrease high blood pressure.
Soy foods can also
lower LDL cholesterol
which may explain the lower associated
cardiovascular disease risk.
Besides the lower breast cancer risk,
soy eaters are also less likely
to get prostate cancer,
colorectal cancer, and lung cancer.
What if you combined
a plant-based diet and soybeans?
Two randomized controlled trials
found that reduced-fat
plant-based diets
with a daily half cup serving
of cooked whole soybeans
can reduce the number
of serious hot flashes
by 84 to 88% within twelve weeks.
Overall, most randomized
to the plant-based group
ended up free of moderate-
to-severe hot flashes,
compared to about 95% still suffering
in the control group.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
premiering at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.